原翻译：D君/LORENZO + TLF字幕组：浮夸/偶蛋腚
修订重译：张一杠磊
没被跟踪吧？
You weren't followed?
没
No.
快请进
Better come in.
吉姆，谁都别信
Trust no one, Jim.
尤其是那些要人
Especially not in the mainstream.
请坐
Sit down.
我知道你仍有一个匈牙利身份可用
I understand you still have one Hungarian identity running?
是的
I do.
我想派你去布达佩斯（匈牙利首都）
I want you to go to Budapest.
秘密行动
This is not above board.
他人不知
Nobody else knows.
他们可是巴不得我失手呢，吉姆小子
They're after my head, Jim boy.
你明白吗？
Do you understand?
我听小道消息说
I have had an offer of service.
一位匈牙利将军要来访
A Hungarian general wants to come over.
我想让你会会他
I would like you to meet him.
他有我要的情报，吉姆
He has some information that I need, Jim.
什么情报？
What information?
重要机密
Treasure.
他知道“鼹鼠”的名字…
He has the name of the mole,
一个俄国佬在英国情报部门安插的内鬼…
the Russians have planted in the British intelligence service
就在“马戏团”的高层中
(“马戏团”即Cambridge Circus,当时英国情报部门的驻地，
下文提到的“局子”也指此）
right at the top of the Circus.
有个内鬼，吉姆
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
我们得把他挖出来
We have to find it.
来点匈牙利炖肉吧，你尝过吧？
是的，我尝过
味道很棒，比土豆牛肉汤强多了，但你现在在布达佩斯吃不到
为什么？
所有的猪都到莫斯科去了
我什么时候能见上你的朋友？
我会带你去见他的，不吃点么？
容我失陪一会？
站住！
Stop!
别开枪！
谁让你开枪的？谁他妈让你开枪的？
该死的业余脑残匈牙利杀手！我要留活口！
看看你都干了些什么，脑残！
骚动什么？都站在原地
我要留活口！
英国秘密情报局首领
参考文献：c/1234
日期：1973年11月14日
帮我做个见证吧？
Would you witness this for me?
我真希望我当时能多帮点忙，老总。
I wish I could done more, Control.
你已经尽力了，珀西
You did all you could, Percy.
作为男人，须知何时谢幕离场
Well, a man should know when to leave the party.
史迈利呢？
What about Smiley?
史迈利随我一起退休
Smiley is leaving with me.
你个小变态，伊斯特哈斯
You little prick, Esterhase.
片名：锅匠 裁缝 士兵 间谍
先生们，我们开始吧？
Gentlemen, shall we start?
安·史迈利夫人
艾瑟顿大街18号
伊斯林顿区
伦敦
珀西先生，副局长拉康在等您
Under Secretary Lacon is ready for you, Sir Percy.
财政部不解
The Treasury don't understand.
情报部门为何不为经费增加的问题
Why can't the intelligence service simply put in a request
提交一个正式的申请呢
for a general increase in funding
那样不就可以支撑你们的专项行动了吗？
and then you account for the spend on your special operation?
“巫术行动”需要保密
Operation Witchcraft needs to remain secret.
- 所以开支由他们自由控制
- 这也是困扰我们的原因
- It's a fiefdom of its own.  - Yes, that's what's worrying us.
整件事难以解释，不是吗？
The whole thing's very unaccountable, isn't it?
没人知道这间伦敦宅子在哪儿
And this London house that nobody knows the address of,
有这个必要吗？
is that really necessary?
比起从前，现在更需要保护
我们苏联情报的来源渠道
Now more than ever. We need to protect our Soviet source.
那你认为我们该在哪接头？咖啡馆？
So where do you propose we meet? In a caf?
房租和费率都翻了倍
The rent and rates on this house have doubled.
我们在核弹头上花了数百万
We spent millions on nuclear warheads.
却不能为一间房子申请几千块
We're asking for a few thousand for a house.
真想知道卡拉是不是也面对着
I wonder if Karla has the same problem
一样抠门的苏联财政部和克林姆林宫
with the Treasury at the Kremlin.
听着，没人低估
Look, nobody underestimates
你们工作的重要性
the importance of the job you chaps are doing.
可去年在布达佩斯发生的事
But what happened in Budapest last year,
着实让人心有余悸
that was a disaster.
恕我直言，先生
With respect, sir,
牺牲的不是您的手下，对吧？
it wasn't one of your civil servants that got killed, was it?
军人在战壕里奋战的时代虽然已经过去
Now this isn't about soldiers in trenches any more.
- 可我们现在干的和在前线无异…
- 罗伊！
- We're the front line now...  - Roy!
过去的25年里，只有我们在阻止卡拉
For 25 years we've been the only thing
standing between them and Karla
莫斯科，以及该死的第三次世界大战
and Moscow and the third bloody world war.
听着，部长大人对你们目前工作的进展表示满意
Look, the Minister's very pleased with your progress so far.
但是他对你们和我们亲爱的美国表亲之间
He's less pleased, though,
缺少协作这点不甚满意
with the lack of progress with our American cousins.
你知道
You see,
在他们眼中
in their eyes,
你们还是一艘漏洞百出的破船
you're still a leaky ship.
什么事？
Yes?
有人找您，先生，好像很急
Someone on the line for you, sir. Seems urgent.
好的，接通吧
All right, well put him through.
- 你好？
- 是副局长拉康吗？
- Hello?  - Is this Under Secretary Lacon?
正是
Yes.
我叫里基•塔尔
My name's Ricki Tarr.
- 有事吗？
- 我想见您
- What do you want?  - I need to meet you.
如果您要核实我的身份，可以找我“马戏团”的上司
If you need to confirm who I am,
you can talk to my boss at the Circus,
彼得•吉勒姆
Peter Guillam.
只有他知道我
But only Guillam, no one else.
允许你骑车进来吗？
You got clearance for that?
我才不会傻得把它锁在外面呢
Well, I'm not bloody chaining it up outside.
友情提醒，和里面这些狠角儿放一起相对安全
Mind you, no better off in here
with this bunch of bloody cut-throats.
他们连你嘴里的消息都挖的出来
They'd have the gold out of your teeth.
我得赶在布兰德之前看一眼新来的妹子
Thought I'd pop in and catch a glimpse of the new girl
before Bland gets to her.
是啊，金发女郎贝琳达
Ah, yes. Belinda the blonde.
- 他见过她没？
- 肯定见过
- Has he seen her yet?  - Of course he has.
今早第一件事就是看她
Came down first thing this morning.
贝琳达
Belinda.
- 我是彼得•吉勒姆
- 你好啊，彼得，我是奥利弗
- Peter Guillam.  - Hello, Peter, this is Oliver.
想问问你…
Just ringing to find out...
这么说是温斯顿•丘吉尔救了你一命，伊迪
So Winston Churchill saved your life, Edie.
当时我在厨房备好了晚餐
I was working in the kitchen, getting dinner ready.
他迟到了
And he was late, you see.
- 突袭的时候？
- 是的
- During a raid?  - During a raid, you see.
他问，你为什么不在那个避难所？
He said, "Why aren't you in that shelter?"
- 你不也不在么？
- 因为我…
- Why weren't you?  - Well, because...
很遗憾听到老总的死讯，史迈利先生
I was sorry to hear about Control, Mr Smiley.
他说塔尔在电话亭给他致电
He said Tarr called him from a phone box.
他说有“鼹鼠”
He said there's a mole,
就在“马戏团”的高层里
right at the top of the Circus,
已潜伏多年
that he's been there for years.
那就是说
It does mean
你最好给我们立即查清楚原委
you're rather well placed to look into this matter for us now,
是不？
doesn't it?
把他清除出去
Outside the family.
我已经退休了，奥利弗
I'm retired, Oliver.
你解雇了我
You fired me.
实际上
The thing is,
老总死前
some time ago before Control died,
曾来找我，暗示我说
he came to me with a similar suggestion.
有“鼹鼠”
That there is a mole.
他没对你讲过他的怀疑么？
He never mentioned his suspicions to you?
没有
No.
噢，我以为你是他的心腹，会跟你讲…
Oh, I just thought that as you were his man, so to speak...
你怎么跟他说的？
What did you say to him?
我想恐怕是他的妄想症在作祟
I'm afraid I thought his paranoia had rather gotten the better of him
再这样下去就要自毁长城了
and he was going to pull his whole house down.
还有布达佩斯的惨剧
That bloody mess in Budapest.
不可否认，乔治
Damn it, George.
他们可是你孕育的一代，是你留下的财富
It's your generation, your legacy.
我本以为，要是这事儿听来有几分可信，
你会愿意…
I would have thought, if there's any truth in it,
you'd want to...
我要彼得
I'll keep Peter.
还有一个政治保安处退下来的人，孟德尔
And there's a retired Special Branch man, Mendel.
我要他
I should like to have him.
提起来
Lift up.
再赶紧关好
And quickly down again.
先生，我知道一个利物浦大街附近的小旅馆
There's a place I know, sir.
A little hotel near Liverpool Street.
请小心点，乔治王时代的
Be careful with it. Please. It's Georgian.
我朋友想要安静工作，波普·格雷姆夫人
My friend wants peace and quiet in order to work, Mrs Pope Graham.
不要打搅他
No disturbances.
她真名只是格雷姆
Her real name is just Graham.
加上波普（“教皇”的谐音）以示高贵
Added the Pope for a touch of class.
彼得，你有老总住处的钥匙吗？
Peter, did you get the keys to Control's flat?
# And did those feet in ancient time #
# Walk upon England's mountains green #
噢！
Oh!
乔治！
George!
乔治快来
George, get in here!
乔治
George.
坐下
Sit down.
看看这些胡言乱语
Take a look at this nonsense.
苏联最高指挥部的
Report by Soviet high command
关于他们近期于黑海的海军演练的报告
on their recent naval exercises in the Black Sea.
正是海军部求咱们
Just what the admiralty has been begging us
弄的情报
for some information on.
- 哪儿得到的？
- 不是我
- Where did you get this?  - I didn't.
珀西和他的小党羽搞到的
Percy and his little cabal walked in with it.
- 听着，老总…
- 闭嘴
- Look, Control...  - Shut up.
文风假得令人无语
Style appalling.
明显从头到尾都是伪造的
Patently a fabrication from beginning to end.
- 也有可能是真的
- 如果是真的，那可价值连城
Just could be the real thing.
Well, if it's genuine, it's gold dust.
不过它到手太快了，令人生疑
But its topicality makes it suspect.
史迈利怀疑你了呢，珀西
Smiley is suspicious, Percy.
哪儿来的？什么渠道？
Where did it come from? What's the access?
我的一个新的秘密线人
A new secret source of mine.
他怎么可能得到这个的？
But how could he possibly have access?
他能参与甚至最机密层级的政策制定
He has access to the most sensitive levels of policy-making.
我们命名这个行动为“巫术”
We've named the operation Witchcraft.
珀西和他的伙计们真是深谙越俎代庖之术啊，史迈利
Oh, Percy and his pals bypassed us, Smiley.
僭越了我们直接找部长去了
Gone straight to the minister.
珀西那位新朋友，连身份都被
Percy has been allowed to keep the identity of his new friend
钦点为最高机密了呢
top secret.
部长也认同这里太多的机密被泄露了
The minister agrees too many secrets are blown around here.
不胜枚举的失败，接连不断的丑闻
Too much failure, too many scandals.
-有用的情报少得可怜
- 珀西有他的道理，老总
Too little solid intelligence.
Percy does have a point, Control.
我们应该反共，而不是内讧
We should be fighting Communism, not each other.
与此同时，我们信誉扫地，损兵折将
Meanwhile we're losing our reputation, our partners.
你们该死的美国佬！
Your bloody Yanks!
我们受够了！得改革了
We've had enough! There's going to be changes.
是时候决定是固步自封还是开创未来了
We need to decide if want to be part of the past
or part of the future.
当年我就不该把你带来
I should have left you where I found you.
- 听着！
- 老总…
- Look!  - Control...
滚，都给我滚出去！
Out, all of you!
如果“巫术”是真的…
If Witchcraft is genuine...
没有什么是真的
Nothing is genuine any more.
乔治…
George...
要我把这些东西带到旅馆吗？
Do you want me to get this stuff over to the hotel?
谢谢，随便放
Thank you. Er, anywhere will do.
- 彼得？
- 嗯？
- Peter?  - Hm?
我要你替我办点事
I need you to do something for me.
[卡拉]
你去“马戏团”
I'd lik e you to go to the Circus.
在值班岗那儿的橱柜里
In the cabinet at the duty officers' station
有最近退休人员的记录
are records of staff recently retired.
拍成照片给我
I'd like photographs of them
还有珀西•阿勒莱恩管理的
“马戏团”发生变动的图表
and of the diagram of the Circus's reorganisation under Percy Alleline,
和所有行动基金的支付清单
along with a list of all payments made from the Reptile fund.
在艾伯特大厅的拐角有一家咖啡厅
是的，三点四十五
不，我没时间弄那个
我知道...
我知道它长什么样
- 比尔，什么事？
- 我在找“陛下”（指珀西）
Help you with anything, Bill?
I was just looking for his Majesty.
他到天台散步去了
Well, he's out walking the battlements.
非常感谢
哦
Oh.
- 听说你受伤了，彼得？
- 开抽屉的时候夹了手
Heard you had an accident, Peter.
Yeah, I cut my hand open on a drawer.
你什么时候去置办些新家具？
When are you going to get some new furniture up here?
我会跟伊斯特哈斯说的，要把这作为决策层的首要大事
I'll have a word with Esterhase.
We'll make it a priority on the top floor.
- 你去哪儿？
- 吃午饭
- Where are you off to?  - Lunch.
一起？
Want some company?
根据人事档案
According to the personnel files,
有七个到了退休年龄
seven were due for retirement anyway.
其他四个也没有太明显的疑点
Another four don't seem particularly mysterious.
杰瑞•韦斯特比于12月4日被解雇
Jerry Westerby was dismissed December 4.
康妮•萨克斯于11月28日退休
Connie Sachs retired November 28.
那是在你和老总被挤走后的两周里发生的
That's just two weeks after you and Control were forced out.
- 回牛津
- 1点15的车
- Return to Oxford, please.  - That's 1.15.
珀西向来反对
Percy has always resisted any proposal
广泛利用“巫术”情报的提议
of a wider exploitation of Witchcraft's intelligence.
别来跟我玩文绉绉的官腔，拉康
Drop the bloody jargon, Lacon.
我至今未跟同盟们分享过“巫术”，部长大人
I've refused to share Witchcraft with our allies so far, Minister.
吝啬的家伙
Greedy boy.
我是想建立一套密不透风的巫术行动情报档案
My goal has been to establish its track record beyond all doubt.
我觉得是时候携手我们的美国盟友了
I think the time has come to approach our American brothers-in-arms.
- 他们会对我们重燃欲火么？
- 我不要一次性交易
Will they take us back into bed?
I'm not interested in a one-off trade.
我要长期的美国情报的分享权
I want on-going access to American intelligence.
你觉得我们能得到吗？
You think we can get it?
只要有“巫术”，我们可以得到任何想要的
With Witchcraft on our side,
we can get anything we bloody well want.
好吧
Fine.
继续下去
Carry on.
谢谢
Thank you.
我要打败你…
And I strike thee down...
哦，我…
Oh, I, er...
想都别想，医生有吩咐
Not supposed to. Doctor's orders.
坏坏的乔治
Wicked, wicked George.
我不知道你怎么想的，乔治
I don't know about you, George,
但我觉得我严重地缺少性爱
but I f eel seriously under-fucked.
我听说安又弃你而去了
I heard Ann left you again.
她配不上你，乔治，连你一根头发都配不上
She doesn't deserve you, George, not one hair on your head.
我退休不久，你也离开了“马戏团”
You left the Circus shortly after I retired.
我是被开除的
I didn't leave. I was dismissed.
被开除的垃圾，和你一样
Chucked out on the rubbish heap, like you.
为什么？
Why?
波利亚科夫
Polyakov.
还记得他吗？
Do you remember him?
苏联大使馆的那位？
From the Soviet Embassy?
阿联克斯•波利亚科夫，以文化交流为由常驻伦敦
Alexsey Polyakov, cultural attache here in London.
15年前他来到这里，我要求对其清查
When he arrived here 15 years ago, I requested he be checked out.
可他记录清白，为人谨慎
He was graded whiter than white. Didn't put a foot wrong.
但你不这么认为？
But you disagreed?
你肯定听闻过这个传说
There's a story you must have heard
卡拉设立了个秘密单元
that Karla has set up a secret cell.
所有成员都是以前军人
The personnel are all ex-military,
训练有素地掌控着资深间谍和“鼹鼠”们
trained to handle deep-penetration agents, moles.
传说是不绝于耳的，康妮
There are always stories, Connie.
万一这个传说是真的呢？
But what if this story was true?
有一晚在调查中我发现了些东西，乔治
One night in research I saw something, George.
我们的朋友波利亚科夫在柏林五一大阅兵中
There was our friend Polyakov at a May day parade in Berlin
收到了一个军礼
receiving a salute.
为什么要向一个文化专员敬礼？
Why would you salute a cultural attache?
显然，除非他是个退伍军人
Exactly. Unless he was a war veteran himself.
若真如此，为何要隐瞒真相？
And if he was, why hide the fact?
你怎么做的？
What did you do?
我直接去找托比•伊斯特哈斯和珀西•阿勒莱恩
I went straight to Esterhase and Alleline.
看
Here.
如果我没弄错的话，波利亚科夫是卡拉训练的人
Polyakov is a Karla-trained hood if ever I saw one.
他若在这儿，说明卡拉安插了“鼹鼠”于此
If he's here, it must be because he's running a mole.
你不要管波利亚科夫
You're to leave Polyakov alone.
你太纠缠他了
You're becoming obsessed with him.
- 不要越俎代庖
- 太荒唐了
- You're losing your sense of proportion, Connie.  - But that's ridiculous.
也许是时候让你回到现实的世界了
Perhaps it's time you went out into the real world.
阿列克斯·波利亚科夫
走就走，反正从前的“马戏团”已经逝去了
What does it matter? Old Circus is gone anyway.
看看这些
Here we are.
我们那时的日子
The nursery in our day.
吉姆•普里多
Jim Prideaux.
当然还有比尔•海顿
俩人黏在一块，和往常一样
And Bill Haydon. Together, of course.
“形影不离的一对”
The Inseparables.
还有老总的独照
There's Control himself.
我的男孩们
All my boys.
我的好战友
All my lovely boys.
那时候多美好啊，乔治
That was a good time, George.
可那是战争年代啊，康妮
It was the war, Connie.
那是一场真正的战争
A real war.
至少那时候英国人还有自豪的理由
Englishmen could be proud then.
我还是对的，是吧？
So I was right, then?
至少关于波利亚科夫
About Polyakov.
确有“鼹鼠”
There is a mole.
若真如此，请勿回来
我想把记忆定格在你们都美好的时候
If it's bad, don't come back. I want to remember you all as you were.
珀西？珀西，你调的这汤？
Percy? Percy, did you mix this?
是，是我调的
Aye, I did so.
你这个小气的没救的苏格兰人
You Calvinistic, penny-pinching Scot.
你这种外行就不能按食谱来做吗？
Can you learn to take a bloody order?
谁也不能乱改食谱！
Nobody tampers with the recipe!
- 我就是按着食谱来的啊
- 别说了
- I followed the recipe.  - Come on.
这猴尿大家喝五个小时也喝不醉啊
It'll take us five hours to get drunk on this monkey's piss.
# He's not the first #
- # He's not the first #  - Oh, well.
圣诞快乐
- # He's the second best secret agent #  - Merry Christmas.
# In the whole wide world
# He's not number one #
# But not the worst #
# He's just the second best secret agent #
# in the whole wide world #
# He's every bit #
# as good as what's-his-name #
# With a dame #
# Any dame #
# And all those bullet holes are in his vest
# To prove you work a little harder #
# When you're second best... #
赫鲁晓夫辞职的次日
他在家，忽然电话响了
一片静默...
“喂？请讲...”还是静默
“说话！我正听着呢！”
答复是：“亲爱的，你本该很早以前就听过了”
- 皮夫人问好
- 嗯？
- Courtesy of Mrs P.  - Hm?
你通宵了？
You been up all night?
是的
Yes.
这是什么？
What's this?
去行动基金要的1000英镑现金
Request for $1,000 in cash from the Reptile fund.
给一个叫埃尔斯的先生
To a Mr Ellis.
吉姆•普里多的一个工作化名
It was one of Jim Prideaux's work names.
普里多一年前于匈牙利遇害
Prideaux was killed in Hungary a year ago.
10月21日
October 21.
那为何还有人于两个月后给他1000英镑？
So why was someone giving him $1,000 two months later?
那我不禁要想他到底现在在哪儿呢？
I wonder where he is then, sir.
该死的车在哪？我们不能失去他，来抬一下
安静
Settle down now.
- 发下去
- 是，先生
- Hand those out.  - Sir.
这是什么？巴黎圣母院的敲钟人？
What is it? The Hunchback of Notre-Dame?
钟，钟！
The bells, the bells!
噢！
Ohh!
出来吧
Come here.
- 叫什么名字？
- 罗奇，比尔•罗奇
- What's your name?  - Roach. Bill Roach, sir.
- 我是新生
- 新来的哦？
- I'm a new boy.  - New arrival, eh?
- 怎么回事？
- 我父亲和母亲
- What's the story?  - My mother and father.
我父亲离开了，所以…
My father left, so...
嗯
Hm.
比尔（账单）
Bill.
未付账的账单
The unpaid Bill.
- 有人那么叫你吗？
- 没有，先生
- Anyone ever call you that?  - No, sir.
我认识很多叫比尔的人
Known a lot of Bills in my time.
他们都是好人
They've all been good 'uns.
你擅长什么？
What are you good at?
一无所长，先生
Nothing, sir.
但你擅于观察，对吗？
You're a good watcher, though, eh?
我们孤独者都如此
Us loners always are.
一旦你带上眼镜，我打赌，比尔•罗奇
Best watcher in the unit, Bill Roach is, I'II bet.
- 你一定是班上最好的观察者，对吗？
- 是的，先生
- Long as he's got his specs on. Right?  - Yes, sir.
很好，非常好
This is good, very good.
你好，里基
Hello, Ricki.
你疏忽了门上的楔子
You've missed the wedge.
你去哪了，里基？
Where have you been, Ricki?
他们追杀我
They're going to kill me.
- 谁？
- 你们的人
- Who is?  - Your lot.
或许是他们的人，无论谁逮到，我都得死
Or their lot. Whoever gets me first.
我是清白的
I'm innocent.
我有我的理由
Within reason.
你来这多久了？
How long have you been here?
对不起，我走投无路
Sorry, I've run out of places now.
我需要见你
I needed to see you.
为什么？
Why?
有一个女人
There's a woman.
我需要你去交易帮我把她从卡拉那弄回来
I need you to trade for her. I need you to get her back off Karla.
什么女人？
A woman?
她叫依瑞娜
Her name's Irina.
去年十一月
This was last November.
吉勒姆先生派我去伊斯坦布尔调查一个俄贸代表
Mr Guillam sent me to Istanbul to check out a Russian trade delegate
这人有被说服投靠我方的可能
who might be persuaded to defect.
- 叫塔夫帝•赛森哲，驻外政治代表
- 就是他
- Tufty Thesinger, resident.  - Yeah.
- 你好，里基
- 旅程还行吧，伙计？
- Hiya, Ricki.  - All right, mate?
- 你认识他？
- 不，没见过
- Did you know him?  -No, never met him.
那人有点嗜酒
Bit of a drinker.
宿醉的鬼样
Hangover from hell.
挺白痴的
Bit of a fucking idiot.
很明显这个叫鲍里斯的俄国人
Apparently this Russian, name of Boris,
混迹于各个夜店，浪荡挥霍
was spending high and wide in the nightclubs.
你就是来游说这个鲍里斯的？
So you were sent to persuade this Boris?
是的，他就是典型的俄国人
Yeah. He was your typical Russian.
天亮贸易谈判，夜晚寻欢作乐
Trade delegation by day, out boozing every night.
乐此不疲
Didn't seem to sleep.
这可把跟踪他的塔夫帝给熬倒了
Tufty was worn out from following him around.'
漫漫长夜啊，孩子
I think it's going to be a long night, son.
他常出没于塔克西姆广场的一个夜总会
His favourite haunt was this club in Taksim.
地下室有个“天上人间”，水手和游客常常光顾
It had a hellhole in the basement where the sailors and the tourists went.
总之，我看他一眼，就觉得我这趟白跑了。
Anyway, I took one look at him and I knew I'd wasted a journey.
鲍里斯不是什么代表
Boris was no delegate.
有哪个代表会醉成这样？除非是装的
What delegate bothers to play drunker than he really is?
我们得学会认出同行，是不是，史迈利先生？
You get to recognise your own, don't you, Mr Smiley?
鲍里斯是莫斯科“中心”
And Boris was a hood
训练出来的间谍
Moscow Centre trained.
# Someone is waiting #
# I mean just for you #
# Spinning wheel #
# Keep on spinning through, Drop all your troubles... #
我猜他在等接头
I guessed he was waiting for a connect.
也可能在搞一个微缩胶卷
Working a letterbox, maybe.
或者拖着他的大衣，在人群中找一个像我这样的人给他信号
Or trailing his coat and looking for a pass from some mug like me.'
所以次夜我去了趟进出口机构
So the second night I went to the import/export outfit
塔夫帝在深处设了间密室
that Tufty had set up with a cipher room hidden in the back.
我发送了“不外售”的电报给吉勒姆先生
I cabled "No sale" to Mr Guillam.
就那样
And that was that.
次日你本该飞回来
You were due to fly home the next day.
是的
Yes.
但你没有
But you didn't.
鲍里斯有一个老婆
Boris had a wife.
法律上的妻子
Common-law.
显然她也是有一席之地的代表团成员
Apparently she was a member of the delegation in her own right.
史迈利先生，您曾教导我相信对女人的直觉
You once told me to trust my instincts about women, Mr Smiley.
我的直觉告诉我，这个女人有料
Well, my instincts told me this woman had some treasure.
那晚当鲍里斯出去后，我告诉自己该去旅馆找她
When Boris went out for the night, I found myself going into her hotel.'
所以你放弃跟踪鲍里斯
So you dropped Boris.
我知道我坏了规矩
I know. It was breaking protocol.
但可以说是我不由自主地在行动
But I was acting on my own initiative, as it were.
你男人真混蛋，不是吗？
Your man's a bit of a bastard, isn't he?
我只是想看看你有没有事，好吗？
I just wanted to make sure you were all right, OK?
所以你没有回来？
So you didn't come home?
本该回的
I would have.
最后鲍里斯那条路是个死胡同，可是…
Boris was a dead end, but...
唔…
Um...
我可以…
I could...
我可以在她身上感觉到某种东西
I could sense something in her.
她有秘密
A secret.
那你打算怎么从她那弄到这个秘密？
And how did you intend to get this secret out of her?
我装成一个叫迈克尔•钱奇的商人
I played this businessman, Michael Trench.
共度浪漫假日
Holiday romance.
我心想不着急
I thought I'd take my time with it.
我知道你的真实身份
I know who you are.
我要跟你的上司谈话
I want to talk to your boss.
老总
Control.
我有东西要交易
I have something to trade.
很重要
Something big.
我想在西方重新生活
I want a new life in the West.
这就是我的要求
That's the deal.
你转告他们
You tell them.
听着，别指望他们对任何情报都欣然接受
Look, you can't expect them to jump at every offer of service.
如果你不能提供更多的情报，我也无能为力
If you won't tell me more, there is nothing I can do.
若我全盘托出
If I tell you everything,
那我就把命交到你的手里了
I'm putting my life in your hands.
还有其他人的命
And the lives of other people.
于是她就告诉了我她要交换的
So she told me what she had to trade.
秘密
Her secret.
我意思是
I mean,
所有秘密的源头
the mother of all secrets.
我告诉她我会通知“马戏团”的
I told her I'd alert the Circus.
她要我保证不能向伦敦透露任何细节
She made me promise I wouldn't give any of the details to London.
- 你同意了
- 是的
- And you agreed?  - Yes.
我意思…
I mean it was...
我都不敢相信我搞到了这么大的情报
I couldn't believe I'd got hold of something this big.
我回到进出口机构
I went back to the import export,
给“马戏团”发了封“最高紧急级别”的电报
sent the message to the Circus, graded, "Flash, highest priority",
说我有一个想叛变的莫斯科同行
just that I had a Moscow-trained hood wanting to defect.
你怎么还没走，伦敦当局找上我了
You're supposed to have gone. London stations have been on to me.
想知道你到底在搞什么鬼
Want to know what the hell you're doing.
滚开
Fuck off.
还有吗，里基？
Anything else, Ricki?
我知道对于“马戏团”，我只是一名头皮猎人
I know what I am to the Circus. I'm one of the scalp-hunters,
那些下作肮脏的任务都可以扔给我干
someone that you can hand your dirty little jobs to.
我只是…
I just...
我只是想把这件事摊给自己而已
I just wanted to bring this one in myself.
我理解你的感受
Well, I understand how you felt.
你想有所成就
You wanted to do something.
我说她有关系到“马戏团”安危的
I said that she claimed to have information
重要情报
Vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
还有吗？
Anything more?
我还说她的情报事关一个双面间谍…
I said that she had information concerning a double agent.
听着，我只想引起足够的重视，而且…
Look, I just wanted to get the proper attention. And I'd...
我告诉他们这就是我当时没有回来的原因
I told them this was the reason why I had not come home.
并不是我叛变了什么的
It wasn't that I'd defected or anything.
- 你之后怎么做的？
- 我等待回复
- What did you do then?  - I waited for a reply.
我来回走了几个小时，还听到了穆斯林的祈祷昭告
I hung around for hours. I remember heard the lmsak call to prayer.
之后，凌晨3点半左右吧
- So what's that time?  - That's about 3. 30 in the morning.'
电报来了
Then the message comes through.
“知道了”
"We read you."
仅此，别无他言
That was all they sent. Nothing.
讲不通啊，他们就像在拖延时间
It didn't make sense. It was like they were stalling.
然后呢？
Then what happened?
突然…
Then, all of a sudden...
俄国佬开始行动了
the Russians begin to move.
手法漂亮，就像我亲自下手的一样
It was nice work. I couldn't have done it better myself.
这信息很明了，我得警告她
The message was quite clear. I needed to warn her. '
哈山...我能用下你的电话么？
可以，用那个吧
快点，快点
Come on, come on, come on.
我在机场找不到她
I looked for her everywhere couldn't find her at the airport.
我几乎查看了所有的班次…
I even looked through all the flight lists and...
还去了港口
I headed down to the harbour.
他们把她押到了去敖德萨(乌克兰港市)的船上
They put her on a ship to Odessa.
我只知道这么多
That's all I know.
我…
I've...
我此生做了很多事情，史迈利先生，可…
I've done a lot of things in my life, Mr Smiley, but...
她却让我难以忘怀
I just... I can't stop thinking about her.
她甚至不是我喜欢的类型
She wasn't even my type.
我得把她弄出来，我欠她的
I've got to get her out. I owe her that.
卡拉会找你的
Karla will be looking for you.
人人都在找我
Everybody's looking for me.
此地不宜久留
You can't stay here.
不安全
It isn't safe.
我说：“你可以对我不屑
但早上见到我你还得管我叫 ‘先生’”
I said, "You may fuck me but you'll call me "Sir" in the morning."
好了，只是想让你知道
OK. Just need to let you know.
有人上周飞达巴黎了，
是我们的人，逃过了护照检查
Someone flew into Paris last week on one of our escaped passports.
- 然后呢？
- 此人就是里基•塔尔
- And?  - lt wasRicki Tarr.
你告诉我这个干什么？
Why are you telling me?
- 可能是巧合吧…
- 你这个脑残死矮子
- It could be coincidence...  - You are a poisoned dwarf.
你为何不滚回你的陛下那儿去？
Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty?
别指望我成为你滑稽秀的一员
and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret
伊斯特哈斯先生说：“可能是巧合吧…”
Mr Esterhase: "It could be coincidence,but..."
海顿先生打断说
Mr Haydon interrupting.
“你这个脑残死矮子”
You really are a poisoned dwarf, Toby.
你为何不滚回你的陛下（指珀西）那儿去？
Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
别指望我成为你滑稽秀的一员
and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret?
你看起来很疲惫
You look tired.
没睡好
I didn't sleep well.
彼得，为我做点事
You're going to do something for me, Peter.
我需要去年11月值班处的登记日志
I need the duty officer's log book for last November.
我不得不更进一步送你去虎穴
I'm going to have to send you up a floor into the lions' den.
你若被逮
If you're caught, you can't mention me.
不能招出我来
很抱歉，可是你只能靠自己
I'm sorry, but you're alone.
- 去年11月的？
- 嗯
- Last November?  - Hm.
吉勒姆先生！
Mr Guillam!
谢谢你，布莱恩特
Thank you, Bryant.
家人还好吧？
How's the family?
挺好的，我今天要上登记处去
Fine. Need to go up to the registry today.
好的
OK, sir.
那你得为你的箱子拿个黄色权限，先生
Now you'll need a yellow one for the bag, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 早安，吉勒姆先生
- 早，阿尔文
- Good morning, Mr Guillam.  - Morning, Alwyn.
- 需要我帮您保管吗？
- 谢谢
- Want me to look after that for you?  - Thank you.
我得看看您的权限，吉勒姆先生
I'll need your chit, Mr Guillam.
上头要是知道我省了这步程序非杀了我不可，
这是新规定
Dolphin will kill me if I don't. New rules.
请便
So, chit me.
谢谢
Thanks.
- 桑儿，很高兴见到你
- 彼得
- So lovely surprise.  - Peter.
- 周末做什么去？
- 你知道的
- What are you up to this weekend?  - Oh, you know.
拜访七大姑八大姨
Visiting aunts.
我猜就是
I'll bet.
D走廊
Corridor D.
中途右侧88号
The two eights are halfway on your right.
111号在下一个凹室
The three ones are next alcove down.
多谢
Thanks.
Here's a request from Libby Barr from Bromley
for Mr Wu's A Window Cleaner Now". Take it away, George.
你好，档案部，我是阿尔文，请讲
Hello. Archive, Alwyn speaking.
我找吉勒姆
Can I speak to Mr Guillam, please? '
我是他的修车工
I'm his car mechanic.
我去看看他是否有空，请稍等
Well, I'll just see if he's available. Hold on, please.
# Mr Wu, what shall I do?#
- 天哪！
- 有你电话，先生
- Oh, Christ!  - Telephone, sir.
- 什么人？
- 外线，一个大老粗
- Who is it? - Outside line, sir. Someone rough.
先生？
Sir?
- 喂？
- 您的变速箱崩了，先生
- Hello?  - Your gearbox is bust, sir.
该死，你难道不会修吗？
Damn it, can't you fix the bloody thing?
不好修
Can't be done. Probably you need a new gear box, sir.
恐怕得换了
给经销商打电话好不，你有他们电话吗？
Well, phone the main dealership first. Have you got their number?
没有
No.
等下，阿尔文！
Hang on. Alwyn!
- 阿尔文
- 什么事？
- Alwyn.  - Sir?
把我的包给我，可以吗？
Get me my bag, will you?
- 可…
- 就一下
- But...  - Just for a second.
谢谢
Thank you.
等下
Hang on.
- 在吗？
- 我在听
- Hello?  - I'm listening.
- 记住了，先生
- Yes. 9-4-6-0-3-3-5.  - Be right on it, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
彼得•吉勒姆
Peter Guillam.
能跟我们见个面吗？
Could we see you, please?
珀西有些紧急的话要跟你说
Percy would like quite an urgent word with you.
如果你现在能去趟五楼，就最好不过了
If you can come now to the fifth floor that would be so kind.
好的
Yes, of course.
替我把这扔到升降机里去
Throw that into the lift for me.
送到三楼，省的我去填那些烦人的单子
Send it to the second floor, save me filling out bloody chits.
放心，先生
Will do, sir.
你最近都在忙些什么呢？
So what have you been getting up to down there these days?
除了调戏我们的黄花大闺女们？
Apart from chasing our virgins.
一些在阿拉伯的行动看上去会有些斩获
A couple of Arab ploys that look quite promising.
除此之外，我在乒乓球上大为精进
Apart from that, I'm getting quite good at ping-pong.
阿拉伯人
Arabs.
你可以租借他们，但无法收买他们,对吧，比尔？
You can rent one but you can't buy one. Right, Bill?
里基•塔尔近来如何？
How's Ricki Tarr these days?
挺好的，我们每天在福特纳姆喝下午茶
Fine. We have tea at Fortnum's every afternoon.
我想知道你与塔尔谈话的内容
I require the matter of your discussion with Tarr.
我会转告他的，他会很兴奋的
I'll tell him. He'll be thrilled.
你耸什么肩？
What's that shrug for?
我在跟你谈论一个叛徒
I'm talking to you about the traitor
他在伊斯坦布尔把我们的人割喉了
who cut the throat of our man in Istanbul.
我在讲一个反水的，而他是该死的你的手下
I'm talking to you about a defector from your own damn section.
我控告你，背着我，与一名敌方特工勾结
I'm accusing you of consorting with an enemy agent behind my back.
所以别他妈的对我耸肩
Don't damn well shrug at me!
要不你去监狱呆上一会？
How would you like a term in prison?
好吧，我没有见过他
Well, I haven't been seeing him.
你能老实点别随便咬人么？
So get your facts straight and get off my back!
那么…我若告诉你塔尔最近到巴黎了
So... if I told you Tarr had recently arrived in Paris,
你会吃惊么？
would you be surprised?
不会的，里基•塔尔的任何动作都不会令我惊讶
No, nothing would surprise me about Ricki Tarr.
那我若告诉你我们偶然发现他的银行账户
And if I told you we happen to know 30,000 mysteriously appeared
多了30000英镑来路不明的钱
in his bank account last month,
你会惊讶吗？
would that surprise you?
你手下是个叛徒，吉勒姆
Your man's a defector, Guillam.
被敌方几个月前收买，如今人家把他派回来了
Turned by the opposition months ago
and now they've sent him back to us.
- 为什么？
- 这不重要
- What for?  - Never mind what for.
就是要弄得我们鸡犬不宁
To muddy the water, that's what for.
散步大量假情报让我们自乱阵脚
To spread a whole lot of damn nonsense to get us chasing our tails.
关键是
The point is this.
他要回英国
He's heading for home.
你看到他的第一眼，就立刻来爸爸们这儿报告
The first peep from him, you come to the grown-ups.
明白？
Understood?
除了在坐的，谁都不许告诉
Anyone you see around this table but not another damn soul.
出去
Get out.
彼得？
Peter?
谢谢你，贝琳达
Thank you, Belinda.
# Oh, Mr Wu #
# What shall I do? #
# Mr Wu... #
还顺利吧？
All go smoothly, did it?
我得去旅馆见乔治
I need to go to the hotel to see George.
史迈利先生不在旅馆，换地方了
Mr Smiley isn't at the hotel, sir. Change of venue.
乔治？
George?
吉勒姆先生…
Mr Guillam...
很抱歉耽搁那么久才回来
Sorry it took me so long to come home.
里基一直在帮我们，彼得
Ricki has been helping us, Peter.
他告诉了我们他的所有经历
He's been telling us all about his adventures.
他是双重间谍，乔治
He's a double, George.
根本没有“鼹鼠”，整个事件都是俄国人一手策划的
There is no mole. Whole thing's been thought up by Moscow.
卡拉用30000块收买他
Karla bought him for 30,000.
为了你我去偷那些文件
I stole that because of you.
我亲自做间谍都是因为他，你知道我的感受吗？
I spied on my own because of him.
Do you know how that makes me feel?
里基…
Ricki...
你说给“马戏团”发电报，提及依瑞娜的情报
you said you sent the Circus a telegram
concerning Irina's information.
- 没错
- 什么时候？
- That's right.  - What was the date?
他不知道，因为就没发
He doesn't know because there was no telegram.
- 整个事情都是他杜撰的
- 11月20日
- The whole thing is a fabrication.  - 20th November.
我清楚的记得是11月20日，晚
It must have been 20th November. Evening.
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
lrina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
高层的每个人都笑得肚子痛
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
- 她告诉我卡拉…
- 11月20日…没有了
- She told me Karla...  - November 20th is missing.
有人销毁了记录，除非你觉得
Someone is covering their tracks, unless of course you think
这是巧合？
that's just a coincidence?
那么钱呢？
What about the money?
用30000块来保护他的“鼹鼠”，对卡拉来说不算多
30,000 isn't so much for Karla to pay if it protects his mole.
恐怕“马戏团”里有人对塔尔了如指掌
I'm afraid someone in the Circus knows all about Mr Tarr
尽其所能去栽赃给他
and is doing everything they can to discredit him.
“马戏团”自认为重要的情报不过是俄国“中心”制造的垃圾
Everything the Circus thinks its' gold is shit, made in Moscow.
你为什么不告诉我你窝藏了塔尔？
Why didn't you tell me that you had Tarr?
...是怕我入了虎穴再也回不来了
In case I never made it out of the Circus.I should get some rest.
我要休息一下
估摸着你也有些阅读工作要做
I suppose you've got your reading to do.
跟我来
Come up.
我见过他一次
I met him once.
卡拉
Karla.
在1955年
In 55.
俄国的“中心”支离破碎
Moscow Centre was in pieces.
一个接一个的清洗
Purge after purge.
他们半数的间谍都叛逃了
Half their agents were jumping ship.
我四处奔走，把他们拉入阵营
I travelled around, signing them up.
好几百号人
Hundreds of them.
有一个自称是格斯特曼的人
One of them was calling himself Gerstmann.
他准备回俄国
He was on his way back to Russia
而我们当时也很确信他回去会被处决
and we were pretty sure he was going to be executed.
飞机要在德里停24小时，我要用那仅有的一天
Plane had a 24-hour lay-over at Delhi and that's how long I had
说服他投靠我们
to convince him to come over to us
别傻乎乎的回国去死
instead of going home to die.
在那个小屋子
There's a little room.
我坐这儿，他坐那儿
I'm sitting here. He's sitting there.
美国佬对他严刑逼供过
The Americans had him tortured.
他连指甲都没了
He had no fingernails.
当时无比炎热
It's incredibly hot.
我很累，只想快点结束，然后回家
I'm very tired and all I want to do is get this over with and get back home.
又跟安闹别扭
Things weren't going well with Ann.
我对他来老的那一套
I give him the usual pitch.
“来西方吧，告诉我们你知道的
"Come to the West and we can give you a comfortable life,
“然后我们给你安稳的生活”
"after questioning."
他怎么回答？
What did he say?
“想想你的妻子
"Think of your wife.
“你有妻子，对吧？
You have a wife, don't you?
“我给你带了点烟
Here. I brought you some cigarettes, by the way.
“用我的打火机
Use my lighter.
“我们能安排她也过来，我们手上有很多交换筹码
We could arrange for her to join you. We have a lot of stock to trade.
“如果你回去，她会被流放的，想想她
If you go back, she'll be ostracised. Think of her."
“想想吧”…
"Think about..."
我一直…
I kept on...
喋喋不休地说他的妻子
harping on about the damn wife,
把自己的很多事也告诉他…
telling him more about me than...
我本该走掉
I should have walked out, of course.
但冥冥之中觉得救他很重要，所以我继续
But for some reason it seemed important to save this one, so I go on.
“你我并非千差万别
"We're not so very different you and I.
“我们都竭尽一生
We've both spent our lives
“想要找出彼此制度上的缺陷
looking for the weaknesses in one another's systems."
“你不觉得现在你该承认
"Don't you think it's time to recognise
“你和我都一样的毫无价值吗？”
there is as little worth on your side as there is on mine?"
他什么都没说
Never said a word.
一个字都没说
Not one word.
次日早晨他回到飞机上
And the next morning he got back on his plane.
他还给我那包烟，没动过
He handed the pack of cigarettes back to me, untouched.
他本是个“烟鬼”，却一根没吸
This was a chain-smoker, you may mind.
他毅然决然地飞向了预想中的死亡
And he flew off to what he presumed would be his death.
他保留了我的打火机
He kept my lighter.
就当是个礼物吧
It was a gift.
“安赠予乔治
"To George from Ann.
“倾吾所爱”
All my love."
他就是卡拉
That was Karla.
他宁愿死也不愿放弃
He went back to die rather than giving in.
而正是如此，我知道他并非无懈可击
Yes, and that's how I know he can be beaten.
因为他是个疯狂的信徒
Because he's a fanatic.
而这些信徒们永远都藏有一个秘密的困惑
And the fanatic is always concealing a secret doubt.
他长什么样？
What did he look like?
记不得了
I can't remember.
从今天起，彼得
After today, Peter,
你必须意识到他们会监视你
you have to assume they're watching you.
若有什么该清理的东西
If there's anything you need tidied up,
赶紧清理
now is the time.
快完成了
Nearly done.
哦上帝啊
For God's sake.
有时我觉得他们都一样的白痴
Sometimes I think they're all sharing the same moronic brain.
如果你有新欢了，你可以告诉我
If there's someone else, you can tell me.
我是大人了
I'm a grown-up.
我知道，这将是个美好的圣诞节
I know. It's just going to be such a wonderful Christmas.
抱歉
Excuse me.
# And I was too proud to give in #
# I had to learn the hard way #
彼得，准备好了
Peter, when you're ready
开始播放
Put it on now.
大家一起！
Everybody!
- 杰瑞
- 乔治
- Jerry. - George.
- 彼得
- 杰瑞
- Peter. - Jerry.
我得跟你谈谈
I need to talk to you.
关于吉姆•普里多遇害的那晚
About the night Jim Prideaux was killed.
那晚你值班，对吗？
You were duty officer, weren't you?
是的，那晚老总让我守着电话
Yeah. Control asked me to mind the phones that night.
他说有人在执行一项特别任务
He said someone was doing a special job for the service.
他要自己信得过的人坐镇
He wanted someone he could trust.
'Hurricane Henry set to be ridden by Ray Walsh at 7:2...'
出事了，长官
There's been a bit of a panic, sir.
这是从外交部过来的消息
This is from the FO resident clerk.
一则匈牙利简要新闻
A Hungarian news bulletin.
“化名为埃利斯的英国间谍
"British spy, work name Ellis,
“利用假护照潜入匈牙利
travelling with false Hungarian papers,
“计划在布达佩斯绑架一名不愿意透露姓名的匈牙利将军
has attempted to kidnap an unnamed Hungarian General in Budapest.
“据悉，此人已被击毙
He's been shot.
“相关逮捕行动已经展开”
Other arrests imminent."
要我做个简报么？
Can I have a brief, please?
长官，您希望我发布否认声明吗？
Sir? Do you want me to deny it, sir?
我得回复，长官
老总一个字也不跟我说
I couldn't get a word out of Control.
我只能按照程序查询了紧急事务的处理方法
So I followed protocol and went for the emergency list.
你打到我家了
You rang my house.
碰碰运气看您是否从柏林回来了
Just on the off-chance you were back from Berlin.
你说什么了？
What did you say?
- 你好？
- 你好，史迈利夫人
- Hello? - Hello, Mrs Smiley.
我是杰瑞，局里的杰瑞•韦斯特比
It's Jerry. Jerry Westerby from the office.
出点小状况
Just that there'd been a bit of a crisis.
安说你尚未回来
Ann said you wasn't back yet and that was it.
然后呢
Go on.
都乱套了
All hell broke loose.
军方说匈牙利的坦克已经在边界上了
Military yelling about Hungarian tanks on the border.
老总和部长开始着急了
Lacon and the minister baying at the door.
谢天谢地比尔•海顿在关键时刻出现了
Thank Christ Bill Haydon turned up when he did.
- 海顿先生
- 现在不行！
- Mr. Haydon.  - Not now.
海顿先生！
Mr. Haydon!
出去！
Out!
- 告诉我发生了什么
- 我试着找过你
- Tell me. - I tried to get hold of you.
我已经从俱乐部的电报上得知大略了，告诉我
I got half a story on the ticker tape at my club. Tell me.
吉姆•普里多中枪了
Jim Prideaux's been shot.
接通匈牙利大使馆
Get me the Hungarian embassy.
你转告你的上司们若敢动吉姆•普里多一根毫毛
You go and tell your masters what will happen
后果自负
if one hair on Jim Prideaux's head is damaged.
让伊斯特哈斯接电话，让他召回我们在匈牙利所有的特工
Get Esterhase on the phone. Tell him to call in the Hungarian agents.
好的，先生
Yes, sir.
有普里多的新消息吗？先生？
Any more news on him? Sir?
天哪
Oh, God.
赶紧去他的住处，清除所有相关的东西
We need to get down to his flat, clear out anything linked.
海顿在他的俱乐部听到了消息？
Haydon heard the news at his club?
在萨维尔俱乐部
It's arguable.
凌晨1：30？那么晚电报肯定下班了
At 1: 30? The ticker-tape wouldn't have been running.
那他是怎么知道的？
So how did he know?
- 天啊，乔治
- 彼得！
- Jesus, George.  - Peter!
- 他怎么知道的？
- 不是你所想的
- Jesus Christ! How could he have known?  - It's not what you think.
- 那他是怎么知道的？
- 那晚他在我家
- Then how did he know?  - Because he was at my house that night.
旅途还行吧？
Good flight?
还行
Yes.
挺好的
Pleasant enough.
我路过，心想拜访一下
I was just passing. I thought I'd call in.
安还在睡，但坚持要起来
Ann was in bed. She insisted on getting up.
她说她一会儿下来
She said she'd be down in a minute.
我带来的，其实是个很烂的涂鸦
That's what I'm dropping off. It's an awful daub really.
不过安说喜欢
But Ann expressed a liking.
她喜欢哪一点？
What's keeping her?
继续
Keep going.
快点，小伙子们，跟上
Come on, lads. Keep up.
快点，比尔！
Come on, Bill!
- 戴上眼镜，胖子？
- 是，先生
- Got your specs on, Jumbo?  - Yes, sir.
过来
Come here.
你看那是谁？
Who's that fellow down there?
我不认识
I don't know, sir.
他是谁？
Who is he?
乞丐？
Beggar man?
小偷？
Thief?
为什么他不看这边，嗯？
Why doesn't he look this way, hm?
换做是你，肯定会朝这群追着车嬉戏的孩子看的
Wouldn't you if you saw a bunch of boys flogging a car round a field?
他怎么回事？讨厌我们？
What's the matter with him? Doesn't he like us?
我不喜欢奇怪的家伙在旁边
I don't hold with odd-bods hanging around.
他可能要偷阿尔维斯？
He might steal the Alvis.
- 阿尔维斯是什么？
- 英国最好的车，先生
- Which is?  - The best car in England, sir.
好小伙
Good lad.
你怎么领到布达佩斯任务的？
How were you briefed for the Budapest mission?
老总让我去肯辛顿（伦敦地名）的一处公寓
Control asked me to come to a flat in Kensington.
有个内鬼，吉姆
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
我们得找出来
And we have to find it.
你是怎么理解的，吉姆？
What did you make of it, Jim?
老总的说法？
Control's theory?
我觉得有点疯狂
I thought it was madness.
我知道是五人之一
I know that it is one of five men.
你只用告诉我他们的代号
All I want from you is one code name.
阿勒莱恩
Alleline. Tinker.
“锅匠”
海顿
Haydon. Tailor.
“裁缝”
布兰德
Bland. Soldier.
“士兵”
我们不用“水手”，读音太接近“裁缝”了
We drop Sailor. It's too close to Tailor.
“阔佬”又不太合适
And Rich Man doesn't seem to be applicable.
伊斯特哈斯
Esterhase. Poor Man.
“穷人”
第五个呢？
And the fifth?
史迈利
Smiley.
我觉得太荒唐了
I thought it was madness.
认为你们五人中有一个是叛徒
To think that any one of you could have been a traitor.
这不是疯了是什么
Absolute madness.
但你还是去了
But you still went.
为什么？
Why?
我去是因为老总之言
I went because Control asked me to go.
这叫尽职
It's called doing one's duty.
在车站我遇到了可以带我去见将军的人
At the station I met the legman who was supposed to take me to the General.
侍者一定是慌了
The waiter must have panicked.
原本是个简单的任务
It was meant to be a simple snatch job.
他们把我带到一个部队医院
They drove me to some military hospital,
然后把我运上运输机
and then put me on a transport plane.
从星星来判断，我们在往东飞
I could tell by the stars we were heading east.
然后他们拷问我…
Then they worked me for...
我不知道拷问了多久
I don't know how long.
几周或者几个月
Weeks, maybe months.
你跟他们说什么了？
What did you tell them?
所有的
Everything.
我尽可能地坚持，让其他人有时间撤离
I held on for as long as I could to let everyone get the hell out of there.
他们逃走了吗？
Did they?
我的匈牙利同伴们得救了吗？
My network s in Hungary, did they get out?
没有，他们全栽了
No, they were blown.
传闻说你为了免受皮肉之苦而告发了他们
The story is you blew them to save your own skin.
当拷问者都走了以后，有个矮个子男人出现了
After the interrogators had cleared out, this little fellow turned up.
像个神父
Looked like a priest.
对我的逼供才真正开始
That's when they really started on me.
你的最后防线是什么？
What was your last line of defence, hmm?
“鼹鼠”
The mole.
老总疯狂的想法
Control's crazy theory.
我将它藏在内心最深处，他们挖不出来
I was going to bury that so deep they'd never get it out of me.
- 结果却是个笑话
- 为什么？
- Which was a joke.  - Why?
因为他们早就知道了
Because they already knew.
他们只是想看看老总到底挖了多深
All they wanted to know was how far Control had got in his investigation.
你认识这个女人么？
No, I don't know her.
告诉阿勒莱恩我们做掉她了
他们没有问起我吗？
Did they ask about me at all?
问过
Yes.
矮个子男人问过
The little fellow did.
他怎么问的？
What did he say about me?
他有一个打火机
He had this cigarette lighter.
他拿着打火机在我面前不停地晃
He kept flashing it about for me to see it.
给我看上面的字
Showed me the inscription.
- “安赠予”…
- “乔治”
- "To George..."  - "... from Ann."
“倾吾所爱”
"All my love."
是卡拉
Karla.
安赠予-乔治
倾吾所爱
太奇怪了
It was odd.
他们把我送回英国
They sent me back to England.
直接到Sarratt（英国南部的一个小村庄）汇报情况
Straight to Sarratt for debriefing.
他说在医院汇报情况的期间还有一位来访者
He said when he was being debriefed at the nursery, he had a visitor.
谁？
Who?
托比•伊斯特哈斯
Toby Esterhase.
他给了他1000块和一辆阿尔维斯
He gave him 1,000 and an Alvis.
并告诉他他现在身份上已经死了，永勿回来
Told him he was dead now. Couldn't come back.
去过安逸的生活，忘掉发生的一切
Had to become a lotus eater, forget everything that happened.
忘掉老总的事情
Control's theory.
忘掉锅匠，裁缝等
Tinker, Tailor. All of it.
我在想
Yes, that's what I thought.
托比•伊斯特哈斯是怎么得知锅匠、裁缝这档子事的？
How on earth did Esterhase hear about Tinker, Tailor?
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
她说卡拉为此颇为自豪
She told me Karla was very proud of this.
她说，“马戏团”自认为重要的情报
不过是莫斯科“中心”炮制的垃圾
She said everything the Circus thinks is gold is shit, made in Moscow.
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
不，附近有家旅馆，他们有几间闲置室
No, I had a hotel nearby. They do have some seedy rooms.
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
她说卡拉以此为乐
She told me Karla was very proud of this...
她说，“马戏团”自认为重要的情报
不过是莫斯科“中心”炮制的垃圾
She said everything the Circus thinks is gold is shit.
这次会面从来都没有发生过，明白吗？
This meeting is not taking place. Is that clear?
明白，部长大人
Perfectly, Minister.
这城市里有栋房子
There is a house somewhere in this city
阿勒莱恩等人在那里跟“巫术”的伦敦代表碰头
where Alleline and the others meet Witchcraft's London representative.
我想拉康跟你说得很明了了
I thought Lacon had made it clear to you.
不要插手“巫术”的事
Keep your nose bloody well out of Witchcraft's business.
我听从的是拉康的建议啊
It's Lacon's advice I'm following.
你让我紧跟老总的脚步的
You told me to follow in Control's footsteps.
想想老总给我们留下的烂摊子，
我不觉得这是个好建议
I wouldn't consider that sound advice, given the mess Control left us with.
花了阿勒莱恩，以及，并非自夸，我本人
It has taken Alleline and, if I may say so, myself
那么久才使“马戏团”重回正轨
this long to get us back in the game.
阿勒莱恩等人会见的那人叫波利亚科夫
The man Alleline and the others meet is called Polyakov.
你以为他的角色就是
从“巫术”带情报给你
You believe his role is to bring information from Witchcraft to you.
其实他真正的任务是从“鼹鼠”那里接收情报
His real role is to receive information from the mole
然后带回给卡拉
to take back to Karla.
这… 不可能
That, er... that's not possible.
可你让这变可能了
Made possible.
就发生在那栋由你说服财政部来买单的房子里
By you in the House which you persuaded the Treasury to pay for.
“巫术”的情报是确凿的，重要至极
Witchcraft's intelligence is genuine. It's been gold.
很小部分有价值罢了
It's just enough glitter amongst the chicken feed.
老总不相信什么奇迹或者巫术
Control didn't believe in miracles or in Witchcraft.
但贪婪又懒惰的你们
But you were lazy and you were greedy,
把他挤出“马戏团”，将卡拉引狼入室
and so you hounded him out of the Circus and you let Karla in.
你们与美国佬协商交换情报
You opened negotiations to exchange intelligence with the Americans.
美国佬告诉“马戏团”的，也会泄露给俄国
What they tell the Circus, they'll be telling the Kremlin.
所谓“巫术”情报，不过是卡拉给你的垃圾情报
Witchcraft's information, the "gold" Karla let you have,
不是在钓你
it wasn't to lure you.
而是在钓美国佬
It was to lure the Americans.
现在
Now,
你还觉得自己立了大功么？
do you want to take credit for that?
我们该怎么做？
What can we do?
我们有一件“鼹鼠”想要的东西
We have one thing the mole wants.
- 如果我去巴黎…
- 你必须去
- If I go to Paris...  - You'll go.
如果我去巴黎
If I go to Paris,
我要你保证你会把依瑞纳弄回来
I want your word that you will get Irina back.
我不管你们用谁交易，我不管
I don't care who you have to trade. And I am out.
我想要个安稳的家，谢谢，我可不想落下你们这样的下场
I want a family, thank you. I do not want to end up like you lot.
你要把她弄回来
You will get her back.
我尽力，里基
I'll do my utmost, Ricki.
你好，乔治
Oh, hello, George.
你好
Hello.
跟我谈谈忠诚吧，托比
I want to talk about loyalty, Toby.
是老总将你招致麾下的，没错吧？
Control recruited you, didn't he?
他在维也纳一个博物馆发现饥寒交迫的你
Found you starving in a museum in Vienna.
还被通缉
A wanted man.
我听说，他救了你的命
Saved your life, I heard.
但在关键时刻
And yet when the time came,
要你在老总和阿勒莱恩之间做选择的时候
when it came to picking sides between him and Alleline,
你毫不犹豫选择了阿勒莱恩
you didn't hesitate.
可以理解，可能是你的战争经历作祟
That's understandable, perhaps, with your war experience.
你能活这么久，我想是因为你那善于改换阵营的能力
You survived this long, I suppose, because of your ability to change sides.
有奶就是娘
Serve any master.
这是怎么回事，什么状况，乔治？
What? What's... What's this about, George?
关于你投靠哪边的主子，托比
It's about which master you've been serving, Toby.
情报在泄漏，托比
Intelligence has been leaked, Toby.
有人在偷“马戏团”的内部资料
Someone's been taking files from the Circus.
不不不
No, no, no, no. No.
这是个误会，误解
This is a mistake, a misunderstanding.
文件传递给了俄国专员，对不对？
Files were delivered to a Russian attache, weren't they?
是的
Yes.
是的，我传递的
And, yes, I delivered them.
但是珀西•阿勒莱恩也参与了
But so did Percy Alleline.
好狗
Good boy.
比尔•海顿也有份
Bill Haydon.
罗伊•布兰德也有份
And so did Roy Bland.
眼见不一定为实，乔治
Things aren't always what they seem, George.
你应该知道
You should know that.
俄方认为波利亚科夫…
Look, Moscow thinks Polyakov's...
在为其效力
working for them.
我们时不时的给些没用的文件让他回去交差
Every now and then we give him the odd file to take back to them.
小部分有价值的也只是为了麻痹他的上司
Chicken feed, just to keep his bosses happy.
但波利亚科夫是我们的人
But Polyakov's our Joe.
- 他是这项大行动的一分子
- “巫术”行动
- He's a part of a big operation.  - Operation Witchcraft.
我知道
Yes, I know.
乔治
George.
- 我不该被这样对待
- 谁让你捎信给吉姆•普里多
- Please, I don't deserve this.  - Who gave you the message
让其忘掉锅匠、裁缝这档子事的？
for Jim Prideaux to forget about Tinker, Tailor?
- 布兰德
- 是谁炒掉康妮•萨克斯的呢？
- Bland.  - To get rid of Connie Sachs?
- 还有杰瑞•韦斯特比？
- 布兰德
- Westerby?  - Bland.
或海顿
Or Haydon.
我不知道，但一定是他们其中之一
I don't know. One of them.
也可能是珀西
Or maybe Percy. No.
好吧，我不知道是谁
Well, I don't know who.
你只是信使
You're just the messenger.
在他们之间跑腿
Running between them all.
传递一切围绕巫术行动的情报
Anything to serve Witchcraft.
你知道的我都知道
I know all about your secret source.
你不知道的，我也知道
And I know something you don't.
我知道谁是幕后人
I know who he is.
是卡拉
He's Karla.
你们中有人给了波利亚科夫很重要的情报
One of you has been giving Polyakov the crown jewels.
- 我不知道
- 你还是被通缉的人吧，托比？
- I did not know.  - Are you still a wanted man, Toby?
- 听着，乔治，我不知道…
- 你站错队了
- Look, George, I didn't know. I...  - You picked the wrong side.
不，你得相信我
No, you've got to believe me.
乔治，求你
George, please.
我很忠诚
I am loyal.
我...我忠心耿耿
I... I am loyal.
不要…不要把我送回去
Don't... Don't... Don't send me back.
求你，乔治
Please, George.
不要把我送回去
Don't send me back.
给我那个地址
Give me the address.
你们在哪儿与波利亚科夫接头？
Where do you meet Polyakov?
嘿嘿！狗狗，安静
Hey, hey! Dog, dog, be quiet!
这是做什么？你是谁？
What is this? Who are you?
- 麦克格雷女士？
- 正是
- Mrs Crave?  - Yes?
- 安全信号是什么？
- 排气孔
- What are the safety signals?  - The air vent.
打开代表安全，关闭代表不便入内
Open and all's well, closed and you're not to enter.
麦克风呢？
And the microphone?
彼得？
Peter?
男孩站在燃烧的甲板上/只有他逃了出来
The boy stood on the burning deck whence all but he had fled;
火焰照亮了遍野的残骸/照亮了头顶的天际
The flame that lit the battle's wreck shone brightly o'er the dead.
他勇敢且骄傲地昂首挺立/仿佛要控制整个风暴
Yet beautiful and bright he stood as born to rule the storm;
鲜活的生灵/虽然是个孩子，但却骄傲地活着
A creature of heroic blood, a proud, though childlike form
火焰翻滚着…
The flames roll'd on...
Merci. Au revoir.
继续
Go on.
整个局里都在搜捕你
The whole service is looking for you.
- 他们逮住你会活剥了你
- 也许我就想让他们发现我呢
- They'll skin you alive if they find you.  - Maybe I want them to find me.
你可以走了，留下册子，把钥匙留在机器上
You can go now. Leave the books and put the keys in the machines.
不，本你留下
No, Ben stays here.
里基•塔尔声称持有关于情报局内部安全的重要信息
Ricki Tarr claims to have information vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
史迈利先生？
Mr Smiley?
的士快到了“马戏团”了
Taxi approaching Circus.
“锅匠”
Tinker.
“裁缝”
Tailor.
这是“士兵”
Here comes Soldier.
到齐了
Full house.
- 大声读出来
- “阿勒莱恩给塔尔的私信
- Well, go on then. Read it out loud.  - Personal for Tarr from Alleline.
“满足你的要求前需解释说明
Require clarification before meeting your request.
“引文，关系‘马戏团’安危的重要情报，结束引文…
Quote, information vital to safeguarding of the Circus, unquote
“太笼统，请发送具体情报”
does not qualify, send further information.
哈，就这样，珀西，你继续拖吧
Ah! That's it, Percy, you keep stalling.
我警告你，本，我们中间真的有内鬼
I warn you, Ben. We've got some really lousy people in this outfit.
我他妈谁都不信
I wouldn't trust a fucking one of them.
会谈结束
The meeting's over.
他们在离场
They're leaving.
如果我们被打搅的话要编个什么故事？
好的，关掉了么？检查下，好么？
确保由你亲自（与塔尔）接头
我们必须在十英里外拦截住塔尔
然后转移走
我是外交使节团的
你们这帮二货无论谁来，都最好牢牢记住这一点！
你该高兴才对
莫斯科可能会授予勋章且奖励公寓给你
我才是那个被流放到西伯利亚去的倒霉鬼
科拉道克斯说几天后就把我送走
Craddox says I'll be off in a few days.
我还在想自己在莫斯科会有多想念板球
（意指“马戏团”和俄国人做了某种交易，将放他回莫斯科）
I keep thinking how much I'm going to miss the cricket in Moscow.
我希望你能帮我打理点事
I was rather hoping you might do a little light housekeeping for me.
尽量
If I can.
有个姑娘，给她些钱，好吗？
There's a girl. Give her some money, would you?
编个故事
And give her a good cover story.
如果能让她好过些，告诉她我爱她
If it helps, tell her I love her.
就这么多
It's all there.
还有个男孩，给他点钱让他闭嘴
And there's a boy, too. Slip him a few quid to shut him up.
我知道审问官们的伎俩，大多是我教的
I know the inquisitors' bag of tricks. I taught most of them.
不过是你来我往而已
It's just a reaction.
或者说是逢场作戏也可
An over-reaction, if you like.
我的确还有一两个问题
I did have one or two questions.
- 关于普里多
- 天哪
- About Prideaux.  - Goddamn it!
- 是我把他救回来的，不是吗？
- 是的
- I got him back, didn't I?  - Yes, yes, you did.
你办的好事
That's good of you.
我惊讶的是卡拉没把他毙了
I am surprised Karla didn't have him shot.
或者你觉得他之所以没痛下杀手
Or do you think he held back,
是为了照顾你的小情绪？
out of delicacy towards you?
普里多在去匈牙利前有没有见过你？
Did Prideaux come and see you before he left on the Hungarian mission?
事实上，见过
Yes, as a matter of fact he did.
说什么了？
To say what?
他是去警告你吧
To warn you.
因为他的直觉告诉他
Because he knew deep down
内奸一直都是你
it was you all along.
你也觉得是我吧
So did you.
我不得不选一边，乔治
I had to pick a side, George.
品位的选择多过于道德的选择
It was an aesthetic choice as much as a moral one.
西方变得丑陋无比
And the West has become so very ugly.
你不觉得吗？
Don't you think?
卡拉有没有考虑过让你接手“马戏团”？
Did Karla ever consider having you take over the Circus?
我又不是他该死的办公室小白脸！
I'm not his bloody office boy!
那你以为你是什么，比尔？
What are you, then, Bill?
我是个建功立业的人
I'm someone who's made his mark.
有什么要我转告给安的吗？
Is there anything particular you want me to pass on to Ann?
那不是针对你个人的，乔治，我希望你能理解
Oh, that was nothing personal, George. I hope you understand that.
卡拉说你是个厉害的角色
Karla said you were good,
是我们重点防范的对象
the one we had to worry about.
不过你确实还有一根软肋
But you do have a blind spot.
他推测如果我成了安人尽皆知的情人的话
He reckoned if I was known to be Ann's lover,
你反而不会那么容易看清我
you wouldn't be able to see me straight.
事实证明他对了
And he was right.
在一定程度上
Up to a point.
先生，我帮你做了这个
I made this for you, sir.
我不想再见到你在这无所事事
I don't want you hanging around here any more.
从今往后，离我远一点
Keep away from me from now on.
- 去加入其他同学们
- 可是…
- Go and join the others.  - But...
就...你就他妈的跟你的同学玩去，好吗？
Just... Just bloody join in, will you?
去玩吧，真该死！
Go and play, damn you!
你能去检查下么，杰瑞？
Could you check, Jerry?
原翻译：D君/LORENZO + TLF字幕组：浮夸/偶蛋腚
修订重译：张一杠磊